

#### PRINCIPAL SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Islamabad, 44000, Pakistan

□ (+92) 303-9421355 | ■ awkhan978@gmail.com | 🖸 a-wakeel | 📓 abdul-wakeel | 🛅 abdul-wakeel-271515aa | 💆 @hexawk

"Be the change that you want to see in the world."

## **Summary**

JAVA Backend Engineer at EmbraceIT with 5+ years experience in backend development, test automation and CI/CD processes. Interested in devising a better problem-solving method for challenging tasks, and learning new technologies and tools if the need arises.

### Skills

**DevOps** Docker, Git, Github Actions, Gitlab Pipelines

**Operating Sys** Linux, Windows

**Back-end** Flask, Django, REST API, Cli Based Apps

**Databases/Data Stores** PostgreSQL, MySQL, SQLite, Redis, KAFKA, RabbitMQ

**Programming** Python, JAVA, JavaScript, SQL, Bash, CMake

**Languages** English, Urdu, Pashto

## Work Experience \_\_

**EmbracelT**Islamabad, Pakistan

SENIOR SOFTWARE ENGINEER

- Currently working as JAVA backend developer with HelloRetail
- Developed and maintaining a sub-product Pages by HelloRetail
- Developed and maintaining a sub-product Analytics by HelloRetail

#### **3G TECHNOLOGIES (GUARANTEE) LIMITED**

Islamabad, Pakistan Apr. 2021 - Oct. 2021

Oct. 2021 - Present

LEAD BACKEND ENGINEER

- Lead a backend team of 5 people towards a successful project initiation
- Participated in the design of a legacy system used by Qualcomm ESG group using modern tools such as python, mysql and linux
- · Planned and designed system with QC ESG team to support backward compatibility with the existing database
- Supported team by maintaining direct communication with ESG
- Designed a pattern for ESG Data Analysis project resulting in minimizing the manual operating procedure by 90%

#### **3G TECHNOLOGIES (GUARANTEE) LIMITED**

Islamabad, Pakistan

SENIOR SOFTWARE ENGINEER

PYTHON DEVELOPER

Mar. 2018 - Apr. 2021

- · Lead the development of DIRBS Core (previously driven by Qualcomm), a data analytics system to identify counterfeit devices over the network
- Designed & managed highly-available Flask based (Python) REST-ful APIs to support OLTP queries to the DIRBS System
- Designed and developed docker based CI/CD solutions for easy deployment of the software, resulting in reduction of manual deployment process by 90%
- · Designed and developed automated scripts for day to day operations of DIRBS to minimize manual processing of data by Ops team
- Introduced redis based in-memory cache to minimize the load on the API server by upto 50%
- Designed and developed real time process monitoring mechanism to continuously monitor queries and process over the time for performance using StatsD, Python Profiler
- Tweaked various existing functionality in the system to make it more space and time efficient
- Provided real time support to the system deployment at Pakistan Telecommunication Authority (PTA)
- Took part in the decision making group related to DIRBS system in the organization
- · Conducted several training's and workshops related to the system in-side and out of the country

#### Experts Vision Engineering and Technology Innovations (Pvt.) Ltd.

Islamabad, Pakistan Dec. 2017 - Mar. 2018

• Designed and developed a system to rank amazon products by identifying real or fake review

- Designed a 3NF database for the system using PostgreSQL to ensure smooth and efficient processing of the data
- Designed and developed an internal IP proxy (rotation system) to minimize IP blocking by 70%
- Designed & managed highly-available Flask based (Python) REST-ful APIs to support OLTP queries to the system

MAY 24, 2022 ABDUL WAKEEL · RÉSUMÉ

Wanclouds Inc. Islamabad, Pakistan

SOFTWARE ENGINEER Aug. 2016 - Jul. 2017

- · Assisted in design and development of system to analyze virtual machine memory state in real time by utilizing Volatility and KVM hypervisor
- · Developed interface to submit and retrieve real time vm memory data to Virus Total using Apache Kafka
- · Worked as software engineer in development of Shepherd, a tool to ensure the different security aspect of containers and VMs
- Participated in end-to-end testing of the products.

## **Training's & Workshops**

#### **Kementerian Perindustrian, Ministry of Industry**

Jakarta, Indonesia

Sep. 2019

TRAINER FOR <DIRBS CORE DEVELOPMENT & UNDERSTANDING>

- Introduced the working of DIRBS and its underlying concepts.
- Introduced how the DIRBS system will work in the country and what will be its impact.
- Helped in understanding the underlying source code and its development and maintenance.

## **Education**

# COMSATS University B.S. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

Islamabad, Pakistan

Sep. 2013 - Aug. 2017